1909 - End of the Ishbalan Civil War
Are you not going back?
帰らないのか
They're going to leave you behind.
置いていかれるぞ
A grave of a comrade?
戦友の墓か
No, an Ishbalan child.
いいえ
イシュヴァール人の子供です
The body was left abandoned on the side of the road.
道端に打ち捨てられていたので
帰ろう 戦は終わった
Let's go back.
The war is over.
Inside my heart, the battle in Ishbal is still not over.
私の中では
まだイシュヴァールの戦いは
終わっていません
No, I'm sure it never will be.
いえ 一生終わらないでしょう
I'm the one who believed in you and entrusted you with my father's research.
あなたを信じ
父の研究を託したのは私
I'm also the one who chose to enter a military academy, wishing for the well-being of the people.
国民の幸福を願い
士官学校に入るのを決めたのも私
Even if that brought an outcome that I didn't wish for,
それが望まない結果になったとしても
I can't escape from the truth.
事実から逃れることはできません
I can't compensate for it.
償いきることなどできません
I have a favor to ask of you, Sir Mustang.
お願いがあります  マスタングさん
Please burn the skin off of my back.
私の背中を
焼いてつぶしてください
How could I do such a-
そんなことできるわけ…
せめて
At the very least!
If I can't compensate for it, then at the very least,
償えないのなら　せめて
I'd like to destroy this secret to flame alchemy on my back,
新たな焔の錬金術師を
生み出さぬように
in order to ensure that the world will never see another Flame Alchemist.
この背中の秘伝を破壊したいのです
Could you please do that for me?
できませんか
Please set me free.
なら　戒めを解いてください
父が私に背負わせたものから…
Please set me free from what my father burdened me with...
From alchemy.
錬金術から　私を解放してください
Please release me from this.
Please.
お願いします
I understand.
分かった
I'll burn it off your back with the least amount of scarring possible.
できるだけ跡が残らないように焼こう
ありがとうございます
Thank you, Sir Mustang.
マスタングさん
The new morning we've finally found
やっと見つけた　新しい朝は
Yatto mitsuketa atarashii asa wa
is being hampered by the past.
月日が邪魔をする
Tsukihi ga jama wo suru
What we chased after wasn't the future,
向かう先は　「次」じゃなくて
Mukau saki wa tsugi ja nakute
but the past so full of remorse.
「過」ばかり追いかけた
Sugi bakari oikaketa
The ruthless memories won't stop playing;
鳴り止まない　容赦ない思い出たちは
Nariyamanai yousha nai omoide tachi wa
they won't be forgiving us for a long time.
許してくれそうにもない
Yurushite kuresou nimonai
It's about now that a teardrop
そろそろかな　手探り　疲れた頬を
Sorosoro kana tesaguri tsukareta hoho wo
beings to roll down my fatigued cheeks.
葛藤がこぼれ落ちる
Kattou ga koboreochiru
Will this rain ever stop?
雨は　いつか止むのでしょうか
Ame wa itsuka yamunodeshouka
I've been freezing for a long time.
ずいぶん長い間　冷たい
Zuibun nagai aida tsumetai
Why does the rain continue to fix on me?
雨は　どうして僕を選ぶの
Ame wa doushite boku wo erabuno
I wonder if it could embrace me.
包まれて　いいかな
Tsutsumarete iikana
Today, the rain falls again;
雨は　止むことを知らずに
Ame wa yamu koto wo shirazuni
endlessly it falls knowing no end.
今日も降り続くけれど
Kyou mo furitsuzukukeredo
We nestle close to each other to share the warmth
そっと　差し出した傘の中で
Sotto sashidashita kasa no naka de
under this umbrella, you gently held out to me.
温もりに　寄り添いながら
Nukumori ni yorisoinagara
What's this about, Lieutenant?
なんのまねだ　中尉
Who do you think you're pointing a gun at?
誰に向かって銃を突きつけている
誰に　笑わせないで
Who?
Don't make me laugh.
The Colonel always calls me 'Riza' when we're alone together.
二人っきりのとき
大佐は私のことリザって呼ぶのよ
Dammit!
So you guys have something going on?!
あんたら　そういう仲かよ
うそよ
Just kidding.
Thanks for falling for it, Envy.
引っ掛かってくれてありがとう
エンヴィー
I'm going to need you to die here.
あなたはここで倒れてちょうだい
That hurts, you bitch!
痛いな
Damn you...!
くっそ…
ばかばか撃ちすぎだ
You shoot too much!
ボロ雑巾にして　大佐の前…
I'll turn you into a rag and show you to the Colonel-
Colonel?!
大佐
What do you think you're doing to my irreplaceable subordinate?
私の大切な部下に何をする
Don't be so reckless, Lieutenant.
ムチャをするな　中尉
I thought I told you I'd take care of him myself.
私が片づけると言ったはずだぞ
How dare a lowly human like you look down on-
クソ人間が見下してんじゃ…
Dammit...!
くっそ…
また　こんな…
This again-
So this is your true form.
それが貴様の本体
You look disgusting.
醜いな
So your name 'Envy' comes from 'jealousy'.
エンヴィーという名は
嫉妬という意味か
Now I get it.
なるほど
No...!
いやだ
やめっ…
Stop...!
Jealousy sure is disgusting.
嫉妬とは  醜いものだな
No! I don't want to die!
いや　死にたくない  い…いや
N-No!
私の視界から…
Get out...
いやだ
PLACEHOLDER
Nooo!!!
...of my sight!
消えうせろ
What's this about, Lieutenant?
なんのまねだ　中尉
That's enough, Colonel.
そこまでです　大佐
I'll take care of the rest.
あとは私が片づけます
One more blow will do the trick.
あと一撃で終わる　銃をどけろ
Lower your gun.
I cannot consent.
承服できません
Please put your hand down.
手を下ろしてください
ふざけるな  どけろと言っている
Stop joking!
I'm ordering you to lower your gun!
Fullmetal.
鋼の　そいつをよこせ
Hand him over.
I'll say it once more.
もう一度言う　そいつをよこせ
Hand him over.
I refuse.
断る
He deserves the worst death possible.
そいつには最低の死を
与えてやらねばならない
I refuse.
いやだ
Hand him over!
そいつをよこせ
さもないと　その右手ごと焼くぞ
If not, I'll set your right arm ablaze along with him!
上等だ　ガチで勝負してやるよ
Well said!
I'll fight you head-on!
But before we get to that, take a good look in the mirror!
けど　その前にてめぇの面よく見やがれ
んな面でこの国のトップに立つつもりか
Do you plan on standing at the top of this country with a face like that?!
That's...
てめぇが…
大佐が目指してるのは
That's not what you've been working your ass off for, is it?!
そんなんじゃないだろ
A subordinate protects their subordinate, and so forth.
下の者が更に下の者を守る
That should be possible, even for us puny humans.
小さな人間なりに
それくらいはできるはずだ
Sounds interesting.
面白そうじゃねぇか
I'm in.
ひと口乗ってやるよ
I want to see what kind of changes
your naive ideals will bring to this country.
お前の青臭い理想がこの国を
どう変えるか見てみたい
So you're going to let your emotions take over
and descend to the path of a savage.
激情に任せ　畜生の道に落ちるか
I guess that's fine.
それもいいだろう
If you're going to insist on living for revenge, I won't stop you.
復讐に生きるというのなら止めはせん
Hey!
オレに他人の復讐を止める資格はない
I don't have the right to interfere with someone's revenge.
I'm just interested to see what kind of world will be created by someone held prisoner by hatred.
ただ　憎しみにとらわれた者が
人の上に立ちどんな世界をつくるのか
見ものだなと思うだけだ
I won't let you kill Envy, Colonel.
大佐には
エンヴィーを殺させません
But still, I don't plan on letting Envy live either.
だからといって　ヤツを
生かしておくつもりもありません
I'll take care of him.
私が片づけます
I...
やっとだぞ…
I finally tracked him down!
やっと追い詰めたんだぞ
I know that!
分かっています  でも…
But...
But what you're about to do isn't for the sake of the country, and it's not for the sake of helping your comrades either.
でも　今　あなたが
やろうとしていることは
国のためでも
仲間を助けるためでもない
You're trying to dispel your hatred.
憎しみを晴らす
That intent alone is gnawing at your heart.
ただ　それだけにむしばまれている
You can't fall down that path.
あなたはそちらに落ちてはいけない
Shoot me if you want.
撃ちたければ撃てばいい
But what will you do after you kill me?
だが　私を撃ち殺した後
君はどうする
I don't plan on living free and easy.
私一人のうのうと
生きていく気はありません
After this battle is over,
この戦が終わったら
I plan on taking flame alchemy, an art that brings about madness, to the grave along with my body.
狂気をもたらす焔の錬金術を
この体もろとも
この世から消し去ります
That won't do.
それは困る
I...
君を失うわけにはいかない
...can't lose you.
What's with this situation, I wonder.
なんだろうな　この状況は
Being scolded by a child,
子供に怒られ
and being cautioned by a man who had been after my life for revenge.
私を敵と狙っていた男に諭され
I made you go through something dreadful again.
君にまたつらい思いをさせてしまった
私は大バカ者だ
I'm the biggest idiot in the world.
I'm sorry.
すまなかった
Are you guys retarded?
バッカじゃないの
きれい事並べてさ
Now you're just sugarcoating your words?
Are you playing a game of "let's be humane"?
人情ごっこかい
You're making my skin crawl.
虫ずが走る
Are you humans really that extravagant?
あんたら人間はそんなにご大層なもんかよ
Just do what your instincts tell you!
本能のままにやりたいようにやっちまえよ
You haven't forgotten, have you, Colonel Mustang?
マスタング大佐　忘れてない
Scar's been after your life!
スカーはあんたの命を狙ってたんだよ
If I recall...
確か　おチビさんの幼なじみの両親を
...it was also Scar who killed the runt's friend's parents too, right?
殺したのもスカーだったよなぁ
そうそう　あのイーストシティの
Oh yeah, and the chimera made from the girl and the dog from East City!
女の子と犬の合成獣
Wasn't it also Scar who killed them?
あれを殺したのもスカーじゃなかったっけ
And on the other hand, you, Scar!
んでもって　スカー
What happened to that hatred you had,
due to so many of your brethren being killed in Ishbal?!
お前もイシュヴァールで
あれだけ同胞を殺された憎しみは
どこ行っちゃったのよ
That woman over there got all puffed up from being called the "Hawk's Eye",
そこの女なんて
「鷹の目」とか呼ばれていい気になって
お前の仲間撃ち殺しまくったんだよ
and shot to death many of your friends!
This is the greatest chance for all of you!
こんなチャンスないって
Come on, just do it!
さあ　やっちまえよ
The cast is assembled!
豪華なメンツだ
Hate, cry, kill, be killed, and writhe in agony!
憎んで　泣いて　殺し殺され
のたうち回れよ
はいつくばれよ
Get down on all fours!
There's no way you pieces of shit can just hold hands and be jolly!
仲よく手ぇつないでなんて
あんたらクソどもに
できるわけないだろ
なあ　おチビさん
Come on, puny runt.
Come on, Hawkeye.
なあ　ホークアイ  マスタング
Mustang!
Scar!
スカー
W-Why?
な…なんでだ…
Hey, why?
なあ　なんでだ
Hey. Hey! Hey!
なあ　なあ　なあ  なんでだ
Why is this happening?!
なんで…なんでなんだ
W-Why?!
Why the hell?!
なんでだよぉ
Envy.
エンヴィー
You're... jealous of humans.
お前　人間に嫉妬してるんだ
Humans are supposed to be a lot weaker than you homunculi,
人間はお前ら人造人間より
ずっと弱い存在のはずなのに
but even if they get discouraged after being beaten, and even if they get close to falling down after losing their path,
たたかれてもへこたれても
道を外れ倒れそうになっても
they continue to get up and fight.
何度でも立ち向かう
Everyone around them helps them get on their feet.
周りが立ち上がらせてくれる
And you're envious of those humans.
お前は
そんな人間がうらやましいんだ
By sacrificing something minor,
you'd be able to save something major.
小を切り捨てりゃ　大は助かる
It's a simple concept if you just think about it.
少し考えりゃ分かることなのにさ
こうすれば　撃てないんだよね
Humans can't shoot me if I do this, right?
人間は
まっ　もっともそれが
Well, that's what makes you all human.
あんたたち人間ってやつだ
でも　どうせ変身するなら
But if I'm going to transform, wouldn't it be better to turn into someone young and pretty?
やっぱり若くてかわいい方がいいよね
人間って　ほんと愚かだよね
Humans are so foolish.
They risk their lives for something so futile.
ムダなことに命懸けちゃったりしてさ
They're human, after all.
やっぱり人間だな
Humans...
人間…人間…
Hey! Stop trying to get away!
こら　逃げるな
Whoa, hang on!
ちょっと待て
バカ  無理に抜けたら…
Idiot! If you force yourself out...!
Ow!
痛っ
Hold it.
待て　もう長くない
He doesn't have much longer.
This is a disgrace.
屈辱だよ
Being turned into a rag like this...
こんなボロ雑巾みたいになって…
Being beaten up by you humans...
あんたら人間に…
Beaten by an existence on the same level as shit...
クソみたいな存在に
いいようにやられて…
And to make matters worse,
しかも　よりによって
a brat like you who's shitty even by a human's standards...
そのクソの中でも
更にクソみたいなこのガキに…
Dammit!
くそっ…くそっ　くそっ
Dammit...!
Dammit!
This is a disgrace!
屈辱だよ…屈辱だよぉ
A disgrace!
このエンヴィーが人間をうらやんでる
I, Envy, am jealous of humans?
このエンヴィーが
I, Envy?!
It's the greatest disgrace...
このエンヴィーが
こんなガキに理解されるなんて…
...to be understood by a brat like you.
屈辱の極みだよ…
I don't know how much longer you can get away with sugarcoating your words,
この先　そのきれい事が
どこまで通じるか
but do try your best.
せいぜい頑張ることだね
Good-bye...
バイバイ…
...Edward Elric.
エドワード·エルリック…
So he took his own life.
自ら命を絶つか…
What a coward.
卑怯者め
傷が治っていく
His wounds are healing!
化け物
Monster!
Hey, what the hell is that?!
なんだ　そいつは
いいところに来た  手を貸せ
Good timing! Lend us a hand!
手を貸せって…
What do you mean?
我々はアームストロング少将
We were ordered to shoot Major General Armstrong!
銃殺の命を受け…
って　少将  少佐まで
What?! Major General!
Even the Major?!
いいところに来た
Yes, good timing.
これより　ここは私が取りしきる
From here on out, I'm in charge of this squadron!
いいから　今は手を貸せ
No questions asked, just lend us a hand for now!
Whoa, what the hell are those?!
なんだ　ありゃ
頭を下げろ
Everyone, duck!
銃弾では効き目はない
Bullets do nothing against them.
上あごをつぶせ
Destroy their upper jaws!
少なくとも
At the very least, they won't be able to bite you to death.
かみ殺されることはなくなる
２人１組で　必ず１匹をしとめろ
Team up with a partner and take down at least one of them.
Show me the courage of the soldiers at Central!
セントラル兵士の勇猛さを
私に見せてみろ
Y-Yes, ma'am!
えっと　なんだっけ
Umm...
What am I supposed to be doing again?
Oh, I remember now.
思い出した
女将軍　殺す
I need to kill the female general.
させぬ
I won't let you!
邪魔
You're in the way.
片腕が使えぬのはやはり…
Only being able to use one arm is a bit...!
少佐
Major!
将軍
General!
あれじゃ　なぶり殺しだ
He's going to get beaten to death!
誰か加勢に行かないと
Someone needs to go help him!
捨て置け　我が弟は
Leave him be!
There's no way a beating like that could bring my younger brother down, considering the way he trains!
あれしきでくたばるような
鍛え方はしとらん
これで  おしまい
This is...
...the end.
少佐
Major!
肩　入ったぁ
My shoulder joint is back in!
That's it!
よし
芸術的筋肉と
A collaboration of artistic muscles and artistic alchemy.
芸術的錬金術のコラボレーション
エクセレント　アンド　エレガント
Both excellent and elegant!
はい　アームストロング邸は
Yes.
The Armstrong Mansion is completely empty.
もぬけの殻です
くそっ　ヤツらここで
Dammit, so they were building tanks in here?!
戦車組み立ててやがったのか
こちら　正門上階
This is the battlements of the main gate!
作戦本部へ
Give me the mission headquarters!
ブリッグズのものと思われる
We're under attack by tanks that are presumably from Briggs!
戦車から攻撃を受けています
作戦本部
Mission headquarters!
がなるな  見えている
Don't shout at me!
I can see that for myself!
かまわん　撃ち返せ
It doesn't matter! Fire back!
But the civilians have yet to evacuate!
しかし　住民の避難がまだ…
そんなもの待っていたら
The main gate will be down if we were to wait for something like that!
正門が落とされるわ
司令部正門砲撃隊に連絡…
Headquarters!
Contact the main gate artillery squadron-
くそっ　何事だ
Dammit, what's going on?!
You're going to open fire on the urban area?
市街地に向けて発砲するだと
それもラジオで流してもらおうか
I'm going to have you repeat that on the radio too.
貴様ら…
You scum...!
その装備はブリッグズの
That equipment is from Briggs!
どうやってここに…
How did you get in here?!
Well, there's a man with a good memory who used to work at Central Headquarters,
元中央司令部勤務で
ちょいと記憶力のいい男が
ここの位置を的確に覚えていてな
and happened to remember this location with pinpoint accuracy.
あとは市街地からここまでの地下道を
There was also a person who dug an underground path between here and the urban area,
一人で掘ってくれた人がいたんだよ
all by herself.
そんなまねできるヤツがいるか
There's no one in this world who could do such a thing!
いるんだなぁ　これが
Oh, but there is.
だっ　誰だ
W-Who?!
誰だと聞かれりゃ
If someone were to ask me who I am, I would tell them I'm a housewife.
主婦だと名乗る
それが私の作法だが…
That's what I usually do, but...
今日ばかりは
I guess today, I'll tell you my other occupation.
あえてこちらを名乗らせてもらおうか
錬金術師だ
An alchemist!
Ever since that day passed,
Ano hi kara zutto
I promised myself that I'd never cry.
Nakanaito kimetekitakedo
But even while I hoarded up the pain,
Itami wo kasanetemo
there was something I couldn't forgive myself for.
Nanika wo yurusezu ni ita
I'll never be able
Mou modorenai
to return to those days.
Ikutsumo no hibi
一人か
You're alone?
I'm still powerless.
Boku wa mada nanimo dekizuni
あの兄弟を
I figured you'd bring your sons.
連れてくるかと思っていたぞ
I watch as the shards of memories disappear, one by one;
Kimi no ita kioku no kakera
おイタをしたガキをしかるのに
It doesn't take very many people to scold a brat who committed a blunder, does it?
何人もいらないだろ
memories of when you were still with me.
Mata hitotsu kieteyuku
フラスコの中の小人
The Dwarf in the Flask,
ホムンクルスよ
Homunculus.
I long to become
Kyou yori motto
stronger than I am now,
Tsuyoku naritai
私に身の一部を与えてくれた
Slave Number 23, the man who gave me a part of his body.
so that my voice will eventually reach you.
Kono koe ga itsuka todokuyouni
奴隷２３号よ
今度は私の体の一部となるがよい
If the wind happens to stop
Arukitsuzukete
This time, you'll become a part of my body.
in the midst of my long journey,
Kaze ga yandara
I'll look up at the sky in search of you.
Kimi wo sagashite sora miageruyo
Beyond the daybreak, a ray of light breaks free.
Yoake no saki ni hikari ga sasuyo
A rainbow spans across the sky.
Niji ga kakaruyo
日本語字幕仕上げ：XIAOBIN
人間よ　今何をなすべきか
Humans, think about what you must do now.
漫遊字幕組
http://popgo.net/bbs
己を示すべき相手は誰か
Think about to whom you must prove yourself to,
なぜ　かくあるべきか
and why this is.
次回　鋼の錬金術師
Next time, Fullmetal Alchemist:
Fullmetal  Alchemist
第５５話　『大人たちの生き様』
Episode 55, The Adults' Way of Life.
誇り高く　胸を張って進め
Walk forward proudly with your head held high.